<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Paules-Crosse the second day of Iune, being the last Sunday in Easter terme. 1622. By Thomas Ailesbury student in diuinitie</title>
            <author>Ailesbury, Thomas, fl. 1622-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00003</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1000</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101513</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837325</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837325</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1641</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00003)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1641)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 691:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Paules-Crosse the second day of Iune, being the last Sunday in Easter terme. 1622. By Thomas Ailesbury student in diuinitie</title>
                  <author>Ailesbury, Thomas, fl. 1622-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Eld for Leonard Becket and Robert Wilson, and are to be sold neere the Temple Church, and at Graies Inne new Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at Pauls-Crosse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1641:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1641:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT <hi>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LES-CROSSE</hi> the ſecond day of <hi>June,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the laſt Sunday in EASTER Terme. 1622.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> THOMAS AILESBVRY Student <hi>in Diuinitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HIERON. in MATTH.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Quoties diem illum cogito, toto corpore contre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſco.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>George Eld</hi> for <hi>Leonard Becket</hi> and <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> and are to be ſold neere the Temple Church, and at <hi>Graies Inne</hi> new Gate. 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1641:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1641:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE LORD, AND REVEREND FATHER in God, <hi>IOHN,</hi> by diuine prouidence <hi>Biſhop of</hi> LINCOLNE, <hi>Lord Keeper</hi> of the Great Seale of ENGLAND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F all created things <hi>(Right Honorable)</hi> which doe in their kinde ſet forth the Creators greatneſſe, <hi>Coeli enarrant, &amp;c:</hi> And in the firmament the Heauens glory; the Sunne, <hi>In Sole poſuit tabernaculum ſuum:</hi> And in the Sunne theſe three, <hi>The glorious light, piercing beames,</hi> and <hi>refreſhing
<pb facs="tcp:1641:3"/> heat</hi> thereof draw with them moſt admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>Man an earthly Sunne, amazeth man to conſider what is in man: But when theſe three, <hi>Learning, Vertue,</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> meet in one man, as in one <hi>Center,</hi> who can but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, who can but to ſuch a man owe, and tender all <hi>obſeruancie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From hence is that <hi>Scitum</hi> of a knowing man; <hi>Honorem eſſe eſcam, Doctrinam hamum, Virtutem rete amorís.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>quorſum iſta?</hi> Say that all theſe (as all muſt ſay who will ſpeake the truth) not onely are, but doe after a goodly propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhine in your Lordſhip; ſhall it not be ſaid preſumption in me (who am as yet but a twig of the <hi>Leviticall</hi> Tree,) to offer my fruits (which may ſeem perhaps but <hi>leaues,</hi>) and that firſt of all to your Selfe, who are ſo firme, ſo fruitfull, and ſo profitable a root, both in our Church, &amp; Common-wealth?</p>
            <p>Yet becauſe both Church, and Common-wealth doe truly ſay that of You, which <hi>St. Bernard</hi> hoped he might ſay of his <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genius,
<pb facs="tcp:1641:3"/> In te facta eſt mutatio, non de te; nec priori ſtatui tuo ſucceſsit promotio, ſed acceſsit:</hi> I repaire to your Lordſhip, though I bring no more to you then <hi>Noahs Doue</hi> did to him; <hi>A little branch in my mouth;</hi> being very ſenſible, that ſeeing it ſprang from a tree in Gods garden, that the onely putting forth of your hand may not onely take me that bring it into the <hi>Arke;</hi> but giue to it growth with a plenteous bleſſing; which being all my ſuit to your Lordſhip;</p>
            <p>I humbly beſeech the God of heauen, to aſſiſt you with his grace, <hi>foeliciter currere, ac foeliciùs in Chriſti pietate conſummare,</hi> to the great good of Church, and Common-wealth here, and to the vnſpeakable good of your owne ſoule, and body hereafter.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours vnfainedly devoted in all obſeruance, and dutie, <hi>THOMAS AILESBVRY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1641:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1641:4"/>
            <head>TO MY MOST worthy Friend.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Rati eſt cui multum debes, ei plurimum velle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere:</hi> All that know me, know that I owe you much more then my ſelfe: And God the ſearcher of the heart, is priuie to my gratefull acknowledgement thereof.</p>
            <p>I dare not expreſſe your kindneſſe, nor your name: for I am well acquainted how pleaſing it is to you to doe well, and vnpleaſing to heare thereof: hauing learn't with <hi>Seneca:</hi> That, <hi>Qui dedit beneficium, taceat; narret qui accepit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The knowledge of the ill ſucceſſe of hiding Talents in the Earth, and your eſpeciall deſire to read, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as to heare; haue moved me to ſuffer this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to be printed. The good therein is Gods, and his grace working in me: The perfection is his, the
<pb facs="tcp:1641:5"/> imperfection mine owne: <hi>For wee haue this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in earthen veſſells.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My chiefe intention was to pleaſe God, and to ayme at his glory: But I know not how, an affection of humane affectation hath interſerted it ſelfe: As that man thinking to ſatisfie nature with food, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares offendeth in gluttony. <hi>Per expoſitionem patefeci dona; per confeſſionem detego vulnera:</hi> In my Sermon I layd open what Chriſtians are to practiſe; and in this confeſsion what in me they are to pardon. God giue a bleſsing to mine indeauours, and a pardon to mine infirmities, and multiply his grace vpon you, and yours in this world; that when theſe temporary meanes faile, you may bee receiued into the euerlaſting habitation.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Seruant in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> Thomas Ailesbury.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults eſcaped in printing, which the Printer prayeth the courteous Reader to correct with his Pen; the Author being abſent.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Fol.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Lin.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Fault.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Correction.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>23.</cell>
                     <cell>paſturing</cell>
                     <cell>paſtoring.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>22.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>areſcet</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>areſcit.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>25.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>And the</cell>
                     <cell>and that the.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>29.</cell>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>caught into</cell>
                     <cell>caught vp into.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>29.</cell>
                     <cell>27.</cell>
                     <cell>Ea-</cell>
                     <cell>Eagles.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>36.</cell>
                     <cell>18.</cell>
                     <cell>*</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>34.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>but ſpeciall</cell>
                     <cell>but by ſpeciall</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1641:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED AT Paules-Croſſe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>LVKE 17. verſe 37.</bibl>
                  <p>Vbicunque fuerit corpus, illuc congregabuntur &amp; Aquilae.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whereſoeuer the body is, thither will the Eagles be gathered together.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT <hi>Adam</hi> did eat of the fruit of the forbidden tree, by faith we conſtantly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it, by experience we wofully lament it. But the<note n="a" place="margin">Habet curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam cognitione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; adhuc incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertam. Pererius in Gen. lib. <hi>3.</hi> q. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſpecies,</hi> or kinde of fruit that he did eat; if it were a Pomegranate, or a Fig; if it were a Grape, or an Apple, holy Scripture hath not expreſſed. The ſubſtance of his fault,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1641:6"/> that he did eat, is recorded; but the circumſtance, what kinde of fruit he did eat, is not at all reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. That lawleſſe eating hath occaſioned a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iudgement; which Chriſt in the Goſpell hath poſitiuely declared; but the time when, and place where that iudgement ſhall be, is not by him in any place diſcloſed: And therefore when his Diſciples would haue preſſed him to it, by a bold, and curious queſtion, <hi>Where ſhall it be Lord?</hi> our Sauiour in my Text ſhapeth ſuch an anſwer, that needs an explication: Intimating thereby Gods counſels to be as deepe waters, which mortall men may not thinke to draine in the hollow of their hands. <hi>Vbicunque fuerit corpus</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>whereſoeuer the body is, thither will the Eagles be gathered together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> propheſied of Chriſt,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.2.</note> 
               <hi>Aperiam in para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolis os meum:</hi> that his lips ſhould diſtill parables. In this Text in part his propheſie is fulfilled: And parables haue in them what <hi>Fulgentius</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally applyeth to the Scriptures;<note n="c" place="margin">In S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ripturis abundat; &amp; quod robuſtus come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat, &amp; quod par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulus ſugat, Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. ſer. de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor.</note> 
               <hi>Et quod ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtus comedat, &amp; quod parvulus ſugat:</hi> Meat for the great ones, milke for the weake ones: And that of<note n="d" place="margin">Diuinus ſermo, ſicut myſterijs prudentes exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet: ſic plerunque ſuperficie ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces refovet: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet in publico vnde parvulos nutriat, ſeruat in ſecreto unde mentes ſublimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um admiratione ſuſpendat. Greg. epiſt. ad Leandr. affix. fronti Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. in Iob.</note> 
               <hi>Gregory</hi> agreeth with euery parable; That which may nouriſh the little ones, <hi>habet in publico;</hi> That which ſuſpendeth with admiration the profoundeſt wits, <hi>ſeruat in ſecreto:</hi> It is a deepe, and yet a ſhallow Ford: <hi>vbi Agnus ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, vbi Elephas natet;</hi> where the Lambe may wade, the Elephant may ſwim: Therein are my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries to exerciſe the prudent, and hiſtories to giue vnderſtanding to the ſimple.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:1641:6"/>
            <p>Some parables the holy Ghoſt<note n="e" place="margin">Intus &amp; feris. Greg. hom. <hi>9.</hi> in Ezech.</note> in the Scripture hath written within, and without: expreſſed, and expounded; and that partly by Chriſt himſelfe: as that of the ſeed, and ſome others; and partly by the Apoſtles, but chiefly by Saint <hi>Iohn;</hi> who was both <hi>ſcriptor,</hi> and <hi>interpres,</hi> (as learned<note n="f" place="margin">Tonſtall. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Euchar.</note> 
               <hi>Tonſtall</hi> ſtyles him) he thought not fit to paſſe ouer the ſayings of our Lord <hi>ſurda aure;</hi> but recorded what our Sauiour ſpake; expounded what he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded: For a view whereof take theſe enſuing particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>expreſſed.</cell>
                     <cell>expounded.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ioh. 2.19. <hi>Deſtroy this Temple, and in three dayes I will raiſe it.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Ioh. 2.22. <hi>This hee ſpake of the Temple of his body.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ioh. 6.55. <hi>For my fleſh is meat indeed, and my blood is drinke indeed.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Ioh. 6.63. <hi>It is the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that quickneth, the fleſh profiteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ioh. 7.38. <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth on me, out of his belly ſhall flow riuers of running water.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Ioh. 7.39. <hi>This hee ſpake of the Spirit, which the beleeuers ſhould receiue.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ioh. 12.32. <hi>And I, if I be lifted vp, will draw all after me.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Ioh. 12.33. <hi>This he ſpake, ſignifying what death he ſhould die.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Now as we are happy in theſe infallible expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of Chriſt, and his Eagle: ſo hence are our teares; that this Text (a parabolicall prouerbe)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1641:7"/> hath deſerued that worth, twice to be recorded by two ſeuerall Euangeliſts; and yet not once to be illuminated by any diuine exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſition. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the<note n="g" place="margin">Ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ta &amp; clauſa ſunt om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia; in ſudore tamen v ltus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem. Aug. in P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l <hi>7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> bread thereof, that is, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, is to be eaten in the ſweat of our ſtudies. I may ſay of it, what<note n="h" place="margin">Hieron ad Pau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in.</note> 
               <hi>Hierome</hi> did of the ſeuen ſhort Epiſtles of the foure Apoſtles; tis myſticall, and ſuccinct: <hi>brevis pariter, &amp; longa;</hi> ſhort, and yet long: <hi>brevis in verbis, longa in ſententijs;</hi> ſhort in words, long in the diuers, but not aduerſe expoſitions thereof: And of them I ſhall deliuer none other then thoſe, which the ancient E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gles of the Church haue deliuered; and which may methodically be reduced to foure generall Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions: In the progreſſe whereof, O God my Redeemer, that <hi>hast the key of Dauid, openest where no man ſhutteth; ſhuttest where no man ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth:</hi> Thou that openedſt thy mouth in parables, open the mouth of mee the ſpeaker; that this parable may at this time be opened to this Aſſembly.</p>
            <div n="1" type="exposition">
               <head>The first Expoſition.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> THe firſt that occurres vnto me (and for the Authors antiquitie firſt to be diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) is<note n="i" place="margin">Origen. tract. <hi>30.</hi> in Matth.</note> 
                  <hi>Origens,</hi> who hath ſenſed the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to be the Church; the Eagles the Doctors; the gathering together, <hi>ſenſus,</hi> and <hi>conſenſus;</hi> the harmonie, vnitie, and conſent in points of faith. And to that in<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 24 28.</note> 
                  <hi>Matthew,</hi> this is very probable:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1641:7"/> where Chriſt premoniſheth his Diſciples; <hi>Take heed that no man deceiue you,</hi> verſ. 4. <hi>Many ſhall come in my name, ſaying, I am Chriſt, and ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue many,</hi> verſ. 5. <hi>Many falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe, and deceiue many,</hi> verſ. 11. Then our Lord pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes rules how to auoyd them: <hi>If any man ſhall ſay, Loe here is Christ, or there is Christ, beleeue it not,</hi> verſ. 23. If they ſhall ſay, <hi>Ecce in deſerto;</hi> behold he is in the deſart, <hi>Goe not forth: behold he is in the ſecret chambers; beleeue it not,</hi> verſ. 26. Then hee demonſtrates as it were with a finger, where he is, that is, where the Eagles are: marke their flight, it guides you to the light: for <hi>vbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque fuerit corpus, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secretae Scripturae rectè Solitudines appellantur:</hi> Scripture ſecretly expounded is a ſecret wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>Baſilides</hi> (ſaith <hi>Origen</hi>) tells me Chriſt is here: <hi>Marcion,</hi> he is in the ſecret chambers: <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinus,</hi> behold he is in the deſart: and bring Scripture with ſolitarie expoſitions to confirme their ſingular opinions. But I beleeue them not,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Sed nos illis cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere non debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, nec exire à prima, &amp; eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtica traditione, nec aliter credere; niſi quemadmodia Eccleſiae tradide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt nobis. Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen: vt ſupra, &amp; tract. <hi>29.</hi> ſub fine.</note> and repaire for the Catholike veritie to the Church, where the paſturing Eagles are.</p>
               <p>No Scripture (ſaith<note n="t" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Peter</hi>) is of a priuate interpretation; which is to be vnderſtood, not <hi>ratione perſonae,</hi> but <hi>ratione modi:</hi> A priuate man may expound, but not in a priuate manner; by ſtamping new expoſitions vpon holy writ, diuers <hi>ab Eccleſiae conſortio</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Quicunque extra hanc do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum agnum comederit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanus eſt: Si quis in arca Noe non fuerit, peribit regnante diluvio. Hieron. epiſt. ad Damaſ. pap.</note>. It is profane to eat the Paſchall Lambe out of this houſe; to gather the flowers of interpretation without the limits of the Churches garden. If any Father, or Doctor,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1641:8"/> ſhall broach any ſolitarie expoſition againſt the Torrent of the Church; we reiect it;<note n="x" place="margin">Noverint Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſe cum Eccleſia Doctores recipe e, non cum Doctorio is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia fidem ſe deſerere debere. Vincent. Lyr. con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tra Nov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. c <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> it being the property of the faithfull, to receiue the Eagles with the body; the Doctors with the Church; and not to forſake the faith of the Church with the Doctors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ex perſonis probamus fidem, an ex fide perſonas?</hi> Doth the faith depend vpon the perſons; or the credit of the perſons vpon the faith? We ought therefore to embrace, what the Church holdeth; The Church to hold, what the Apoſtles haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered; The Apoſtles hauing deliuered, what Chriſt taught; who taught nothing but what he receiued of the Father; as<note n="y" place="margin">Quod E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia ab Apoſtol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, Apoſtoli a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto, Chriſtus a Deo accepit, ſine dubio tenendum. Tertull. praeſcript. adverſ. haereſes.</note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> iuſtly preſcribes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Origen</hi> himſelfe, whoſe houſe was<note n="*" place="margin">Vincent. Lyr. vt ſupra.</note> 
                  <hi>illuſtrata martyrio,</hi> famous for martyrdome, himſelfe ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>totius doctrinae magnificentia,</hi> with all the magnificence of learning; yet when hee began to ſet on foot priuate <hi>Tenets,</hi> and <hi>Gloſſes:</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Origenes in acre dom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>num gloria pro daemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus impudenti crucifigit men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacio. Bernard. ſer. <hi>54.</hi> in Cant.</note> As, that the paines of the damned ſhould not be eternall; and that Chriſt ſhould be crucified in the ayre againe for the deuils; as he was on earth for man; herein we reiect this Eagle, becauſe hee was not gathered to the body.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vincent. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yr.</note>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> a worthy Ancient, famous for his Apologies for the Chriſtians; for his writings for the Chriſtian faith; whom <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> reuerently eſteemed as his maſter;<note place="margin">Da magiſtram.</note> yet when this Eagle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to doate in his old age vpon the dreames of <hi>Montanus,</hi> and his aſſociates; who held them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues equall to the Apoſtles in diuine reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1641:8"/> we ſay; <hi>Hic magister non tenetur;</hi> and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in reiect this Eagle, as gone out from the body.</p>
               <p>But when the lightning ſhall ſhine from the Eaſt vnto the Weſt, when the Weſt and Eaſterne Eagles, the Doctors of the Greeke, and Latine Church ſhall meet in one harmonicall center of agreement; as they did in the foure firſt Generall Councels; we thinke it more then common in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolencie to diſſent from them: But when the lightning hath ſhone in the Weſt, and darkneſſe vpon the face of the Eaſt: and when the Weſterne Eagles ſhall decline from the Church, wee leaue thoſe, and cleaue to them that are gathered to the bodie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Hierome</hi> in his time complaines to <hi>Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> how the<note n="a" place="margin">Hieron ad Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſ. pap. teſtatia vaſa, vel lignea. Non vaſtitas Elementi liquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, &amp; interia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens longitud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> terrarum &amp;c. Nunc in Occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente Sol Iuſtitiae oritur, in Oriente Lucifer ille, qui ceciderit, poſuit thronum ſuum. Idem vt ſupra.</note> Eagles of the Eaſt had degenerated: nothing but weeds, ſowre grapes, thornes, and thiſtles growing in their garden: therefore hee had his recourſe to the Sunne, that then ſhone in the Weſterne Church: not the depth of the ſeas, not the length of the earth, could ſeparate him from this light, for ſayes he, <hi>Whereſoeuer the body is, thither will the Eagles be gathered together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as his complaint was of the corruption of the Eaſt; we iuſtly reſume it, bewayling the now declined eſtate of the Weſterne Church: That the Eagle of Rome, the Patriarke of the Occiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Church, hath taken her flight from her body; lamentably muſing with the Prophet; <hi>How is the faithfull Citie become a harlot.</hi> Rome, ancient Rome,<note n="b" place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tius praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deres religione divina, quam do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatione ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rena. Leo in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. Apoſtolorum Petri, &amp; Pauli, ſer. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> famouſed more for thy religion, then conqueſts: ſacked thou art of thy pretious mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garite
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1641:9"/> of faith, and veritie: That thy Pope is<note n="c" place="margin">Reverendiſs. Epiſcopus Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton. in reſponſ. Apol. pro Iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento Fidelita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis contra Bellar.</note> 
                  <hi>alius à Chriſto,</hi> another from Chriſt, we doubt not: But if <hi>alius ab Antichriſto,</hi> another from Antichriſt, we deſeruedly call it into queſtion.</p>
               <p>The like complaint make we of the inferiour Eagles of Rome, of their new deuiſed expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to vphold their drooping, and dying cauſe: To inſtance but in one, (who is in ſtead of all) Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who hath tranſlated Chriſt into the Pope: That Stone, that corner Stone, that pretious corner Stone, and ſure found<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion, which<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſay</hi> 28.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> the Prophet foretold: and<note n="e" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> the Eagle applyed vnto Chriſt,<note n="f" place="margin">Jn Hiſtrionica ſua praeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> affix in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b. de Rom Pont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> hath ſquared it for the Pope: He can conuert <hi>omnes</hi> into <hi>ſolos:</hi> Chriſt ſaith of the Chalice,<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.27.</note> 
                  <hi>Drinke you all of this;</hi> that is, (ſaith hee)<note n="h" place="margin">Clariſsimè pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet verba illa ad ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>los Apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pertinere. Bellar. de Sacram. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi> §. Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>igit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</note> the Prieſts alone: and <hi>manducationem in Monarchiam;</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 10.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter kill and eat, ergo Peter</hi> was Head of the Church: Therefore wee reiect this, and ſuch Eagles; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue not kept them to the body.</p>
               <p>And hereby we deſcry the Browniſts, and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſts to be no Eagles: thoſe erring ſtarres that haue no fixed motion in the Churches <hi>orbe;</hi> who in ſtead of reſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ting to the body, doe cut off themſelues from vs by a ſchiſmaticall rent.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Expoſ. in Matth <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>S. Chryſostome</hi> obſerueth, that our Sauiour ſaith not, <hi>exite;</hi> but <hi>nolite credere:</hi> goe you out; but beleeue them not: But like an expert Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, prohibites all excurſions from the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches bounds, <hi>nolite exire,</hi> goe not out: Beleeue them not, auoid hereſie: Goe not out, take heed of ſchiſme: Say our Church be deformed, yet
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1641:9"/> ſhee is not infectious: Say the chaffe is mingled with the wheat; Do we for the chaffes-ſake for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the threſhing floore of the Lord? Saint<note n="l" place="margin">Greg paſtoral. part. <hi>3.</hi> admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Gregory</hi> notes, that our Lord in the Goſpell ioynes ſalt, and peace together;<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.50.</note> 
                  <hi>Haue ſalt with your ſelues, and peace one with another: Sal ſinc pace, non virtutis est donum, ſed damnationis argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum.</hi> Let your ſalt of doctrine ſeaſon the Church with a peacefull vnion: for the one with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other, is not virtuous, but vitious.</p>
               <p>But moſt of all that Father, Biſhop, Martyr, <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t admirable Treatiſe of his, <hi>De vnitate Eccleſiae,</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th battered this forlorne er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror:<note n="m" place="margin">Hanc vnita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem qui non te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, tenere ſe fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem credit? Solis multi radij, ſed lumen vnum. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi arboris multi, ſed robur vnum: de fonte vno rivi plurimi defluunt, numeroſitas licet diffuſa videatur, vnitas tamen ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatur in origine. Cypr. de vnit. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae nu. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> The vnitie of the Church he that holdeth not, doth he thinke he holdeth the faith? Many beames iſſue from the Sunne, yet but one Sunne: diuers Riuers ſtreame from the fountaine, yet but one head: many branches ariſe from one root, yet but one tree; breake off a branch, <hi>fractus ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minare non potest,</hi> it withereth, it dyeth: ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate a Riuer from the fountaine, <hi>praeciſus are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcet,</hi> it dryeth vp: and ſo no hauing of God for our Father, vnleſſe we take the Church for our Mother.</p>
               <p>Let not <hi>Novatian</hi> a Separatiſt boaſt of his morall gifts, and rectitude of faith, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe may be in him: <hi>Chriſtianus non est, qui in Eccleſia Christi non inest:</hi> He is no Chriſtian, that is not in the Church of Chriſt: He may giue all his goods to the poore, and his body to be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, yet<note n="*" place="margin">Non erit illa fidei corona, ſed poena perfidia. Idab. nu. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>occidi potest, coronari non potest:</hi> If he die without the Churches limits, killed he may
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1641:10"/> be, crowned with martyrdome he cannot be. Hitherto <hi>Cyprian.</hi> Certes this ſequeſtration ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them to be no Eagles, who are not gathered to the body. All this while haue I fought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Origens</hi> banner; I leaue him now, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the ſecond expoſition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="exposition">
               <head>The ſecond Expoſition.</head>
               <p>ANd thats of<note n="n" place="margin">Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>on. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in Matth.</note> 
                  <hi>Hierome,</hi> and<note n="o" place="margin">T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. in l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us proper no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mortius eſt in caſam poſitas. Matth <hi>24.</hi> Iob <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>9.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l.</note> 
                  <hi>Theophylact,</hi> who conceiue by <hi>the bodie</hi> to be meant Chriſt ſuffering, and dead vpon the Croſſe: by <hi>the Eagles</hi> the Saints, whoſe gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are waſhed in the blood of the Lambe: and by the <hi>gathering together,</hi> the efficacie of his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: <hi>Whereſoeuer the dead body is,</hi> as <hi>S. Matthew</hi> hath it; and in <hi>Iob, Whereſoeuer the wounded,</hi> or <hi>ſlaine is;</hi> which reading <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ophylact</hi> keepeth, not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; to which alſo<note n="p" place="margin">Hae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>tia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſimilitud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ris <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a. Bez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ann. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>1</hi> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er.</note> 
                  <hi>Beza</hi> doth aſſent, not the body, but the carcaſſe, to which the Eagles are gathered.</p>
               <p>Holy Scripture proclaymeth that Chriſt ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that Chriſt died for vs vpon the Croſſe: witneſſe the<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>lib.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Tormentors, that abſtained from breaking of his leggs, becauſe he was dead alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; witneſſe <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 27.58.</note> 
                  <hi>Arimathea,</hi> that petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to <hi>Pilate</hi> for his body, wownde it in linnen cloathes, laid it in a graue, which was ſigned with the common ſignet, where it abode three dayes till the reſurrection: witneſſe himſelfe, <hi>he bowed his head,</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 19 30.</note> (ſaith the Scripture) <hi>and gaue vp the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1641:10"/> Ghost:</hi> He bowed himſelfe, whom the Crucifiers could not bowe; and gaue vp the Ghoſt, gaue it vnto his Father, who gaue it vnto him. <hi>Quod amittitur neceſſarium est,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ambroſe.</note> 
                  <hi>quod emittitur volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium:</hi> In amiſſion the act is neceſſarie, in emiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on voluntary: <hi>Quis ita dormit quando voluerit, ſicut Ieſus mortuus est quando voluit?</hi> Who could euer fall aſleepe ſo when he would; as Chriſt died when he would?<note n="t" place="margin">Aug. tract. <hi>119.</hi> in Iohan.</note> 
                  <hi>Quis ita veſtem deponit, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do voluerit, ſicut Ieſus mortuus est quando voluit?</hi> Who euer laid aſide his garment ſo, when hee would, as Chriſt ſtript himſelfe out of his fleſh, when he had a will ſo to doe? <hi>Quis ita cum vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luerit abijt, quomodo Chriſtus cùm voluerit, obijt?</hi> Who ſo willingly departed any whither, as Chriſt out of this world, when he ſaw his time? according to that prediction of <hi>Eſay, Oblatus est, quia voluit:</hi> whereof <hi>S. Bernard</hi> giues the reaſon; <hi>Ipſe oblatio, &amp; offerens;</hi> He was the Prieſt, and the Hoſt; the ſacrifice and the Sacrificer: <hi>Natus est,</hi> and <hi>datus est, paſſus est,</hi> and <hi>mortuus est:</hi> no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his birth, and death, but his charity that made him will; his will anſwerable to his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
               <p>In the<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.8.</note> 40 Pſalme: <hi>Sacrifice, and burnt offering thou wouldst not haue, but a body haſt thou ordayned me:</hi> which latter clauſe though it anſwer not the Originall; yet the<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Septuagint ſo tranſlate it; the Apoſtle to the<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 10 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Hebrewes</hi> ſo quotes it; and<note n="y" place="margin">Aug. enarrat. in Pſal. <hi>39.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Augustine</hi> ſo reads it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A body hast thou ordayned me:</hi> a true body, not a phantaſticall, as <hi>Manicheus;</hi> a terreſtriall, not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1641:11"/> a celeſtiall body, againſt <hi>Valentinus;</hi> a body that might really ſuffer, and not appeare to ſuffer, againſt <hi>Hilary;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>10.</hi> de Trin.</note> a body like vnto our body, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Hoſt of our redemption was to be, <hi>&amp; noſtri generis ſocia, &amp; noſtrae contaminationis alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> ſayes<note n="a" place="margin">Ser. <hi>3.</hi> in Nat. Domini.</note> 
                  <hi>Leo;</hi> like vnto vs in nature, for whom he ſuffered; vnlike vnto vs in ſinfull nature, for which he ſuffered.</p>
               <p>The Deity was impatible; no paſſion, no ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, no griefe, could faſten vpon the Godhead: the ſting of death could not pierce the diuine ſubſtance: God could not ſuffer, could not be wounded, could not be nayled to the Croſſe, could not dye;<note n="b" place="margin">Cum mortis aculeum non poſsit accipere natura Deitatis; ſuſcepit tamen naſcendo, &amp;c. Leo ſer. <hi>8.</hi> de Paſsione.</note> therefore <hi>ſuſcepit ex nobis, quod poſsit offerre pro nobis;</hi> He tooke that of vs, that hee might offer for vs: a body capable of the Croſſe, of the paſſions vpon the Croſſe, of the death of the Croſſe.</p>
               <p>He tooke it, and he offered it, like vnto the Moone, <hi>acceptam refero,</hi> all the light receiued from the Sunne by reflection, ſhee communicates vnto vs inferiour creatures: <hi>Verbum caro factum est,</hi> the Word was made fleſh, there he tooke it; and that fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt the way of all fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh, for hee died; and ſo offered a body, that might, and did ſuffer; a body that might and did dye vpon the Croſſe: His natiuitie was <hi>praeludium paſsionis,</hi> a paſſage to his paſſion: Borne hee was, that hee might liue; liue that he might worke; worke that he might ſuffer; ſuffer that he might die; die that we might liue, and be borne againe: and ſo came he from heauen to the wombe, from the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1641:11"/> wombe to the Cratch, from the Cratch to the Croſſe, from the Croſſe to the graue: And thus <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> was turned into <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; a body into a dead body, <hi>He died for vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And though by death Chriſts body was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſoule; yet not without God.<note place="margin">Vnio naturarum indiſſolubilis.</note> The ſoule for a time was parted from the body; The Godhead neuer was diſtracted either from ſoule or body: The diſſolution was in one of the natures, not of the natures: for if the natures had beene diuided, there had beene a double ſubſiſtence; and ſo by conſequence a double perſon, which was the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie of <hi>Neſtorius:</hi> The Godhead is wedded to the Humanitie without all poſſibilitie of diuorce: Our Sauiours ſoule in his Agonie, felt not the preſence of the Godhead; yet <hi>non ſoluit vnionem,</hi> though <hi>ſubtraxit viſionem;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leo.</note> the viſion was eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the diuine vnion was not diſſolued: The bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die in the graue enioyes not the ſoule; yet though the ſoule departed, the vnion was not parted: The paſſion of Chriſt (ſaith <hi>S. Auſten</hi>) was the ſleepe of his Diuinitie: and by the like propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may I ſay, The death of Chriſt was the ſleep of his Humanitie: yet heres the difference; In the paſſion, the Humanitie was forſaken of the Deity, but apparently; the body of the ſoule re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally: Life was ſeparated, yet the <hi>Hypoſtaſis</hi> remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. So great is the vnion betwixt God, and man, <hi>Vt nec ſupplicio poſsit dirimi, nec morte diſtingui;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leo.</note> That neither death, nor paſſions could breake it aſunder.</p>
               <p>The Schoolemen obſerue, that there is <hi>Vnum
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1641:12"/> per vnitatem,</hi> and <hi>vnum per vnionem,</hi> The Father and the Sonne are one by conſubſtantiall vnitie: God and man are one by Hypoſtaticall vnion; In the Father, and the Son there is <hi>alius,</hi> &amp; <hi>alius,</hi> not <hi>aliud,</hi> and <hi>aliud,</hi> a perſonall difference, but a naturall vnity: In Chriſt there is <hi>aliud,</hi> and <hi>aliud,</hi> not <hi>alius,</hi> and <hi>alius,</hi> a naturall diſtinction, but a perſonall vnion. The Godhead in one act aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Manhood both ſoule, and body, and as <hi>vna eſt aſſumptio,</hi> ſo <hi>vna eſt vnio,</hi> the vnion is but one; by vertue whereof he is vnited to ſoule, and body. For a demonſtration hereof, <hi>Bonauenture</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Bonav in <hi>3.</hi> Sent. diſt. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> obſerues in that vnion three things; 1. <hi>Actio vnibilis;</hi> 2. <hi>paſsio vnibilis;</hi> and 3. <hi>relatio vnibilis:</hi> the firſt is whereby God aſſumed man; ſo the Word was made fleſh: the ſecond, whereby the humanity ſubſiſteth in the Deity: the third, as there is a double relation had to ſoule, and body: So Chriſt is vnited by one act, but yet by a double relation to ſoule, and body: double in power, in the aſſumption of the humanity: double in act, in the diſſolution of the humane nature.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee the body without a ſoule by death, but not without the Godhead: diſiointed, not diſunited: diſſolued in nature, not diuorced in perſon: So we haue ſeene the body made a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kas, let vs now ſee the collection, the gathering together.</p>
               <p>Foure things in Chriſt to vs are very obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant: 1. his calling; 2. his inuiting; 3. his ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering; 4. and his drawing of vs: For the firſt he ſaith,<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Venite ad me, &amp;c.</hi> Come vnto me all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1641:12"/> ye that are weary, and heauy laden, &amp;c. For the ſecond;<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 14.17.</note> He ſent his ſeruant at ſupper time, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite the gueſts, &amp;c. For the third,<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37.</note> Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem, how often would I haue gathered thee together, &amp;c. And for the fourth,<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.32.</note> If I be lifted vp, will draw all after me. Oh the peruerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of man! Chriſt calleth; we ſtop our eares at the voyce of this celeſtiall Charmer: he inuiteth, but we make excuſes: hee would gather vs, but wee would not: yet when theſe will not ſerue, (O rare mercy!) he draweth; <hi>Trahit inuitos,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rn.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; facit voluntarios:</hi> He draweth vs vnwilling, that he might make vs willing to be gathered.</p>
               <p>I am now ſpeaking of his gathering together, and ſee with what paſſion, and compaſſion hee ſpeakes to Ieruſalem: Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37.</note> and O Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, I would gather; and how often would I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thee; gather thee as a Hen, and as a Hen her Chickens; her Chickens vnder her wings: The damnable obſtinacy of the Citizens that did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe it.</p>
               <p>See how oppoſite Chriſt is vnto Sathan: Chriſt he gathereth, the deuill diſperſeth: Chriſt gathereth as a Hen, the deuill diſperſeth as a Lyon; Chriſt vnder his wings, the deuill within his jawes.</p>
               <p>The Prophet <hi>Dauids</hi> prayer was,<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.</note> Protect me vnder the ſhadow of thy wings: then were Chriſts wings diſplayed, when his armes were ſtretched out vpon the Croſſe; then were his armes, and body open to embrace thee; opened indeed, by the nailes, by the ſpeare, by the thornes; and ſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1641:13"/> he did both <hi>cor,</hi> and <hi>brachia,</hi> and <hi>latus aperire,</hi> ſaith<note n="i" place="margin">In Lucam <hi>14.</hi> cap.</note> 
                  <hi>Stella:</hi> opened all for thee, that heauen might be opened to thee; ſee the gathering to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               <p>The Eagles then, the Saints muſt, and doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort to this body, and let it be our practice, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort vnto it, by a commemoration of his death, by an application of his merits.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Let vs remember him who hath remembred, and thus remembred vs, as to call, to inuite vs, to draw, and to gather vs together. <hi>Domine quid eſt homo?</hi> Lord what is man? that thou ſhouldeſt thus remember him? Man, forlorne man: man, rebellious man: man, ſinfull man: And, <hi>homo, quid eſt Deus?</hi> Man, what is the Lord? that hee ſhould remember thee: the Lord that made thee, re-made thee: the Lord that gaue thee life, died for thee, &amp;c. It was <hi>Opus ſine exemplo, gratia ſine merito, donum ſine pretio, charitas ſine modo,</hi> ſaies melliſluent <hi>Bernard:</hi> A worke not to be ſampled, grace not to be merited, a gift not to be priſed, charity not to bee meaſured: While the firſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Dormit Adam vt fiat Eua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, moritur Chriſtu vt fiat Eccleſia. Aug.</note> ſlept in the garden, <hi>Eue</hi> was framed: while the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> ſlept in the graue, the Church was formed: when the body was a carkas, were the Eagles gathered together.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Let vs gather together his merits to vs, to make them efficacious;<note place="margin">Ieſu eſto mihi Ieſus.</note> That Ieſus would be to vs a Ieſus. This it is to build our neſts in the clefts of the Rocke: The Rocke is Chriſt, the clefts are the wounds of Chriſt: to build our neſts, is by intereſting our ſelues through faith in his merits:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1641:13"/> 
                  <hi>Vt ille</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
                  <hi>ſit ſalus in te, qui ſuſcepit vulnera propter te:</hi> That he might be a plaiſter, an Antidote to thee, that was wounded for thee: and remember,<note n="m" place="margin">Leo.</note> 
                  <hi>Non itur ad Chriſtum, niſi per Chriſtum:</hi> no flying to Chriſt but by Chriſt: therefore he ſaith,<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.6.</note> I am the way, the life, and the truth. I am the way which leadeth to the truth; I am the truth that promiſe life; I am the life which I lay downe for the life of the world: <hi>Clamat errantibus, Ego ſum via; clamat dubitantibus, Ego ſum veritas: clamat laceſcentibus, Ego ſum vita:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> Chriſt is the way for vs to walke, truth vs to direct, life vs to refreſh.</p>
               <p>Theſe things conſidered, let vs take our Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles wings, that we may be ſafe vnder the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his wings; and flye vnto the body: So where the body is, ſhall the Eagles be gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: And thus much for the ſecond expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="exposition">
               <head>The third Expoſition.</head>
               <p>THe third generall Expoſition,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. Theoph. St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lla. Ferus. Maldonat. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ. in Loc. &amp; Mat. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> wherein the major part of Interpreters agree. That in theſe words an adumbration of the laſt iudgement is contained: For in the precedent verſe, Chriſt ſpeakes of the<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 30.</note> day, and that day and his day, when<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 31.</note> the Sonne ſhall be reuealed. And compares it<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 37.</note> to <hi>Noahs</hi> time, the old world, and the flood; To<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 40.</note> 
                  <hi>Lots</hi> time, Sodom, fire, and brimſtone: &amp; tels vs, how ſome ſhall be acquitted,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1641:14"/> and others condemned; Two men labouring in the field; the one ſhall be receiued, the other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed:<note n="s" place="margin">
                     <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e</hi> 41.</note> Two women grinding at a mill, the one ſhall be accepted, the other reiected: And then ſhuts vp all with this Epiphonema; <hi>Vbicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit corpus, &amp;c.</hi> and ſo here is <hi>vbicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi> for <hi>vbi, corpus</hi> for <hi>Chriſtus, Aquilae</hi> for <hi>animae;</hi> nothing expreſſed, yet all prefigured: an anſwer that needs an anſwer: a reſolution that needs an explication: with a, Lord ſhew vs this parable: Whereſoeuer the body ſhall be, &amp;c. there is the <hi>Cortex,</hi> the <hi>husk:</hi> but whereſoeuer Chriſt ſhall be, &amp;c. there is the <hi>Medulla,</hi> the <hi>ſap.</hi> The body then is Chriſt the Iudge, the Eagles are the Saints, the gathering to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether is the generall Iudgement: This is the <hi>Center,</hi> whereunto the <hi>Circumference of my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations</hi> is to be gathered together.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note>The body is Chriſt, Chriſt is the Iudge: as <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliauit ſcipſum,</hi> to dye for man, to be iudged by man; ſo <hi>exaltauit cum Deus,</hi> to iudge his Iudges: and ſo is fulfilled that of the Apoſtle, The ſtone which the builders not onely <hi>improbauerunt,</hi> but <hi>reprobauerunt,</hi> not diſliked, but vtterly refuſed, is become the head ſtone in the corner.</p>
               <p>In the<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.22.</note> fifth of <hi>Iohn, the Father iudgeth no man, but hath committed all iudgement to the Sonne:</hi> the Father hath ſurrendred, and reſigned all iudgement into the hands of his Sonne: And therefore hee ſaith, <hi>The Father iudgeth no man, but the Sonne.</hi> Before it ſeemed by Chriſts words the Father did, what the Sonne doth not; the Father loueth the Sonne, and ſheweth him all
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1641:14"/> things that he doth: <hi>tanquam Pater faciebat, &amp; Filius videbat,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) as if the Father were the Worker, the Sonne the Spectator: there I beheld <hi>Patrem facientem, Filium expectantem:</hi> the Father the doer, the Son the looker on: here I ſee <hi>Patrem vacantem, Filiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudicante<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> the Father at leaſure, in vacation; the Sonne iudging in a full Court,<note n="u" place="margin">Quid hoc eſt paulo ante puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bamus facere aliquid Patrem, quod non facit Filius. Aug. tract. <hi>21.</hi> in Ioan.</note> (Lord) thou art the profound word of the Father, I am ſhallow man, &amp; vnderſtand thee not: (Bleſſed Sauiour) I heare thee ſpeaking of thy ſelfe; I iudge no man, there is another that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, &amp; iudgeth: <hi>ille quaerit iniurias tuas, ille iudicat de iniuriis tuis;</hi> who ſo meet to ſeeke after thy wrongs, and to iudge them that haue wronged thee, as thy Father? How can it bee then that the Father iudgeth no man, but hath committed all iudgement to the Sonne? <hi>turbamur hic, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bati deſudemus, deſudantes purgemur:</hi> we are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled here, being troubled, we ſweat to enucleate the myſtery, and in deſcrying thereof we are pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. All iudgement is therefore giuen to the Son, not that the Father will ceaſe to iudge: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Pater occultus erit, Filius manifeſtus:</hi> The Father ſhall iudge, but not be ſeene to iudge; the Sonne ſhall iudge, and be ſeene to iudge: becauſe he ſhall iudge in the habit of a man.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 10 42.</note>
                  <hi>Him,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>hath God ordained to be Iudge of the quick, &amp; dead:</hi> where you may ſee his commiſſion, &amp; his circuit: his commiſſion, deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the King of Kings: <hi>Constitutus à Deo:</hi> him hath God ordained: his circuit, the largeſt that euer was; Iudge of quicke and dead: that is,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1641:15"/> of the iuſt, and vniuſt: ſo <hi>Lyranus.</hi> Of the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſoules, and mortall bodies, ſo <hi>Ruffinus.</hi> Of the dead before, and of thoſe that are found aliue at the reſurrection;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <hi>for we ſhall not all die, but ſhall be changed;</hi> ſo <hi>Caietan.</hi> Large it muſt then needs bee, that is extended vnto all.</p>
               <p>We ſee then by this time, what we are to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to that Queſtion diſcuſſed in the Schooles: If Chriſt in <hi>forma humana,</hi> ſhall iudge the world: out of doubt hee ſhall come againe in the ſame manner, that he went from vs into heauen:<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 1.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niet, &amp; ſic veniet,</hi> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h a body, with the ſame bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me body, with the ſame skarres: as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> teacheth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He hath giuen all iudgement vnto the Sonne:</hi> the Father could not giue it to the Sonne as God, which was his owne by nature; neither could Chriſt receiue that, which as God he neuer wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:<note n="y" place="margin">Datum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Patre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> iudi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iumait, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> quia poteſtatem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ſe na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ra no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> habeat, ſed per <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſpen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> homo Cyril in Ioan. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b. <hi>2.</hi> cap <hi>140.</hi>
                  </note> But the Father hath giuen, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sonne receiued as man: as man ſhall hee come in the Clouds; as man ſhall he ſit vpon the throne; as man ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll he denounce the ſentence; as man ſhall he be ſeene of all: the Godhead ſhall bee perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous to the godly onely: But Chriſt as man, ſhall lye open to all mens eyes; to the faithfull, to the vnfaithfull, <hi>confuſis, &amp; confiſis,</hi> to the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, to the crucifiers: according to that of the Prophet,<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10.</note> 
                  <hi>They ſhall looke on him whom they haue pierced.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt as God,<note n="a" place="margin">Tolle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ex of in Ioan. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erſ. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> iudgeth with the Father in common; as man, alone: ſome workes there be which Chriſt doth <hi>in carne,</hi> and yet cooperateth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1641:15"/> with the Father: Some workes which he doth <hi>per carnem,</hi> wherein he worketh alone, and the Father by him: as we ſay truly <hi>Maries</hi> Sonne created the world, Chriſt <hi>in carne</hi> created the world, but not <hi>per carnem,</hi> by the fleſh. So Chriſt in the fleſh, raiſed <hi>Lazarus;</hi> but not by the fleſh. So Chriſt ſuffered by the fleſh, (for the Deity could not be touched with paſſion) but trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phed in the fleſh: So the Father and He as one God ſhall iudge together in the fleſh; but not by the fleſh: in which reſpect as man he ſhall iudge alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Part.</hi> 3. <hi>q.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6. <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tic.</hi> 2.</note>
                  <hi>Aquinas</hi> giues three reaſons for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, for the conueniency, moſt ſutable to man, to be iudged by man.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, for the equitie: Good reaſon Chriſt ſhould iudge man, who for man, was iudged by man: <hi>Sedebit Iudex, qui ſtetit ſub Iudice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> 
                  <hi>damnabit reos, qui falso factus est reus:</hi> There ſhall he ſit to iudge, who ſtood here to be iudged; &amp; condemne the guilty, who falſly was accuſed to be guilty.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, becauſe good, and bad are to be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: Now the wicked were not to behold the Godhead, in the preſence whereof there is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ioy; therefore was Chriſt to iudge as man.</p>
               <p>This queſtion in Schooles begets another, <hi>viz.</hi> whether, this iudiciall power were giuen to Chriſt, as man, freely, or purchaſed by his merits? The Schoole-men anſwer, that it was giuen to him, <hi>gratia capitis,</hi> by the grace of perſonall vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For when God aſſumed man, he infuſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1641:16"/> the Humane nature all thoſe graces the Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie was capable of; and yet they ſay it was me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited by him too. He humbled himſelfe to the loweſt; therefore God hath exalted him to the higheſt.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> What hindreth (ſaith <hi>Tho. Aquin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> but that one and the ſame thing may be due by a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble title; of gift, and purchaſe? Chriſt on earth was both <hi>viator,</hi> and <hi>comprehe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſor: extra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>num,</hi> and <hi>in termino;</hi> abroad and yet at home: therefore being in a meritorious eſtate, and his merits of an infinite value what was it that hee could not m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rit?<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bonaue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ture</hi> makes a twofold merit: 1. Whereby a thing is due which was not due before. 2. Whereby it is due more wayes then it was before. The <hi>praemium ſubſtantiale,</hi> though it were giuen him by grace, and ſo due: yet he might purchaſe it by his merits, and ſo make it more wayes due then it was before.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee all things plead for Chriſt to be the Iudge: It belongs vnto him eſſentially, as God: perſonally, as giuen from the Father: and meritoriouſly, whereby Chriſt, by vertue of his merits may deſeruedly claime it. So haue wee ſeene the body, Chriſt the Iudge: I proceed to <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gles,</hi> the parties to be iudged.</p>
               <p>By <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Eagl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> are meant the Saints: And of thoſe Saints there is a fourefold expoſition rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Maldonatus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is the bleſſed Soules, which en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oy Chriſt now in heauen, of whom <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh,<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> 
                  <hi>They follow the Lambe whither-ſoeuer he goeth.</hi> The Lambe is <hi>the body:</hi> The following is <hi>the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1641:16"/> together: Theſe are they, that haue waſhed their robes, and made them white in the blood of the Lambe; hee that ſitteth on the throne dwelleth among<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> them, and the lambe ſhall feed them for euermore in the midst of the throne:</hi> Their P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtor the Lambe: The place of paſture, in the midſt of the throne.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond, the Saints that then ſhall be found aliue at the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſurrection:<note place="margin">Sancti <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <note n="g" place="margin">1 <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 4 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Then we which are aliue, and remaine, ſhall be caught <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p together with them in the clouds to meet the Lord in the ayre, and ſo ſhall we be euer with the Lord.</hi> And againe;<note n="h" place="margin">1 <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 15.5.</note> 
                  <hi>We ſhall not all ſleepe, but ſhall be changed in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the twinckling of an eye.</hi> Hereupon many of the<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 42.</note> Ancient haue thought, that ſome at that day ſhall paſſe without death to life; though <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> ſay, <hi>Lord, who is that man, that ſhall not ſee death? Shall he deliuer himſelfe from the power of the graue?</hi> And the Apoſtle tells vs, that it is a ſtatute agreed vpon in the Parliament of heauen;<note place="margin">Heb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Statutum est omnibus mori,</hi> all to die, and ſo to iudgement. But <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſeemeth to determine this doubt; though <hi>a ſleepe</hi> ſhall not be, yet <hi>a change</hi> ſhall be in ſtead of ſleeping: <hi>Shall not ſleep;</hi> that is, ſo long as others that haue lyon long buried; ſo<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> men. &amp; A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſelm. in <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Occumenius. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tà dormitio breuiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>na, non tamen nulla;</hi> ſo<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> men. &amp; A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſelm. in <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Anſelmus; Shall not all ſleepe,</hi> that is, continually, but ſhall be awaked, ſo<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Lorinus;</hi> to meet in the clouds the Lord of glory.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third is of the attendance of the Angels, Saints, and Martyrs, vpon the Lord of glory.<note place="margin">Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rtes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 25 31.</note> 
                  <hi>Then ſhall you ſee the Sonne of man come in glory,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1641:17"/> and the holy Angels with him, in the clouds, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and great glory.</hi> For <hi>qualis Rex, talis praepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio Regis,</hi> ſayes the Author of the imperfect perfect worke vpon <hi>Matthew:</hi> and <hi>Dignitate do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini honorata ſit conditio ſerui;</hi> The glory of the Iudge ſhall be eminent in his followers, and the Saints ſhall be glorified in attending vpon the Lord of glory. Of this ſaith the Apoſtle,<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ſ.</hi> 3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>When Christ who is our life ſhall appeare, then ſhall we appeare alſo with him in glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth, that by <hi>the Eagles</hi> are meant all the Saints,<note place="margin">Sanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ere.</note> from the firſt day of the world till the laſt day:<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> for <hi>they without vs ſhall not be made perfect.</hi> Theſe elect Eagles ſhall come from the foure quarters of the world, and ſhall ſit downe with the Patriarkes in the kingdome of heauen.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee all agree, that by <hi>the Eagles</hi> are meant the Saints only: therefore he ſaith not the Vultures, or ſuch foule Fowles, though it be their property likewiſe; but the Eagles are gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: In them to note the regalitie of the Saints. And this the<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Gloſſe obſerueth; <hi>duo quaerentibus vnum reſpondet;</hi> of the two labourers in the field, the Diſciples demand, where the one, and the other ſhall be: Chriſt he anſwers for his, that they ſhall be gathered; and leaues them to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what ſhall become of them which are none of his; they ſhall be reiected.</p>
               <p>Tis true, the Eagles doe not riſe alone, but they ſhall be gathered alone. The Vultures ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, the wicked ſhall ariſe, but to condemnation. Damnable is that Rabbinicall conceit; that none
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1641:17"/> ſhall riſe, but thoſe that ſhall be ſaued. And the wicked by this corporall death ſhall be vtterly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct in ſoule, and body; grounding themſelues vpon thoſe miſtaken words of the<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>à radice</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> which ſignifies to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e or ſtand.</note> Pſalme, <hi>The wicked ſhall not riſe in iudgement: non, quod non reſurgant; ſed quod in iudicio non reſurgant:</hi> he ſaith not, that the wicked ſhall not riſe; but in iudgement they ſhall not riſe, ſaith<note n="r" place="margin">Hieron. in Pſal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Hierome:</hi> they ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll not<note n="ſ" place="margin">Cyri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. Hieruſ. Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g.</note> riſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith <hi>Cyrill</hi> of <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> As Felons, whoſe fact be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euident, are placed at the barre; not ſo much to be conuicted as to be condemned: Their ſins, their conſcience, &amp;c. ſhall ſo accuſe, that the Lord Iudge will not make any great inquiſition to find out their fault, but preſently proceede to ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Greg. Moral. in Iob. lib. <hi>26.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>S. Gregory</hi> obſerues, that of the wicked and the godly, the Eagles and the Vultures, there ſhall be a fourefold manner of proceeding in iudgement.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt of the wicked: <hi>Quidam iudicantur, &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reunt;</hi> ſome are iudged, and condemned, <hi>periſh by iudgement:</hi> ſuch as haue drawne neere vnto God with their lips; but are farre from him in their hearts:<note n="u" place="margin">Idem ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Profeſsionem fidei retinentes, opera profeſsionis non habentes:</hi> Hold ng a profeſſion of the faith, but not works of that prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſion. Theſe mens cauſe ſhall be heard, <hi>I was hungry, but you fed me not, &amp;c.</hi> Such men ſhall be weighed in the ſcales, and ſhall be found to be light; <hi>ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in iudgement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, of the wicked: <hi>Quidam non iudican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1641:18"/> &amp; pereunt:</hi> Are not iudged, and condemned; <hi>periſh without iudgement:</hi> Notorious ſinners, that would not be curbed vpon any termes: Of them the Apoſtle ſpeaketh,<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 2.12.</note> 
                  <hi>As many as haue ſinned without the Law, ſhall periſh without the Law.</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Greg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſupra.</note> 
                  <hi>Neque enim neceſſe est lege perimi, qui lege nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam potuit teneri:</hi> No nec ſſitie that the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe liuer ſhould be tryed by a l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w; as his life knew no law, ſo his death ſhall be without law; <hi>ſhall periſh without iudgement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, of the godly, whereof <hi>Quidam iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantur, &amp; regnant,</hi> are iudged, and quitted, <hi>ſaued by iudgement.</hi> Secular men that vſe the world, are often foyled in the world, and recouer by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. Their cauſe is heard; <hi>Eſuriu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp; ded<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis mihi; I was hungry, and you fed me &amp;c</hi> and the ſentence pronounced for them; <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my Father, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, of the godly, <hi>Quidam non iudicantur, &amp; regnant</hi> are not iudged and raigne, <hi>ſaued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iudgement.</hi> Saints that haue tranſcended or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie holineſſe, hauing abſtained from things lawfull, becauſe not expedient; that they might be the more at liberty to ſerue the Lord. Such were the Apoſtles:<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Chriſt; Ecce reliqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus omnia; Behold we haue left all, and followed thee: Christ</hi> to <hi>Peter; You</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o many as haue thus followed mee) <hi>ſhall ſit vpon twelue Thrones, and iudge the twelue Tribes of Iſrael.</hi> Thus wee ſee the Saints ſhall not riſe alone, but ſhall be ſaued alone: The Eagles onely to the body ſhall be <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:1641:18"/>
               <p>It is not amiſſe in the next place, to conſider, wherein the Eagles doe reſemble the Saints; and that's in fiue properties enſuing<note n="z" place="margin">Gorr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n. expoſ. in locum, &amp; Matth. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>4.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is: The Eagles moolt off their old fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and ſo become bald: The Saints of God doe ſo plucke off their ſinfull feath rs from the ſoule, that they become bald like vnto the Eagle: They crucifie the old man with the luſts; weed out ſinne by the roots. The Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting the people to repentance, bids them<note n="a" place="margin">Micah <hi>1.</hi> vlt.</note> 
                  <hi>to inlarge their baldneſſe like the Eagle: Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen</hi> did more then caſt her feathers, when ſhee conuerted her <hi>eyes,</hi> her <hi>haire,</hi> her <hi>lips,</hi> feathers of wantonneſſe, into pledges of Repentance: Her eyes that allured in my, diſtild riuers of teares: Her haire that inſnared many, ſerues her for a Towell to wipe her Sauiours feet: Her lips which had inticed many, ſerues her to kiſſe, &amp; not ceaſe to kiſſe the ſame feet, her teares had waſht, her haire had wip'd: And ſo, <hi>Quot oblectamenta, tot holocauſta,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory:</hi> The baits to vanitie, are conuerted into <hi>Holocauſts</hi> of Repentance.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond reſemblance is in the new birth;<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.5</note> 
                  <hi>Who reneweth thy youth like vnto the Eagle.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at one novi homin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> The E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gles breake their bills vpon a ſtone, and ſo are renewed in their age: The rocke is Chriſt, vpon whom the Saints breake their hearts by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and ſo in their ſoules are renewed. <hi>Paul</hi> had c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt his bill, and feathers too, when he ſaid,<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Galath</hi> 2.20</note> 
                  <hi>Now I liue not, but it is Christ that liueth in me. Extinctus fuit ſaeuus perſecutor; &amp; viuere cepit pius Praedicator,</hi> ſaith<note n="d" place="margin">Homil. ſuper Si quis vult ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Gregory.</hi> The ſword is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1641:19"/> turned to the word, perſecuting into preaching; and he that breathed out threatnings againſt the men of God, breathes out Gods threatnings againſt the men of this world: and ſo was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed like vnto the Eagle.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third is in the cleareneſſe of viſion: The Eagles can looke vpon the Sunne:<note place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>o is la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tate. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> The pure in heart can ſee God: but the light ſhineth in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the darkneſſe comprehendeth it not. Our Lord<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> pronounceth the Diſciples eyes to be h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ed are the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yes that ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the things that you ſee, &amp;c.</hi> A ſpeciall prerogatiue that hath beene d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d to Kings, and Kings deſiring to ſee: to Prophets, and many Prophets, which hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not ſeene them.<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Beat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>on quia diuites, &amp;c.</hi> Bleſſed, not becauſe you are rich, you are great, you are mighty: but becauſe you haue ſeene; haue ſeene <hi>Adam</hi> and his loſt by ſinne; <hi>Adam</hi> and his recou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red by Chriſt; haue ſeene God become your Sauiour; and ſhall ſee your Sauiour come to iudgement.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth reſemblance is in their lofty flight:<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 39.27.</note> 
                  <hi>Doth not the Eagle mount vp,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>and make her n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> on high,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob.</hi> So is it with the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ints, as their conuerſation, ſo their contemplation is as high as heauen: Humble hearts, yet lofty thoughts, that reach the skies.<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 5. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues, that in the glaſſe of contemplation there are three ſteps to the diuine viſion: 1. <hi>Aſcenſus:</hi> 2. <hi>Exceſſus:</hi> 3. <hi>Raptus:</hi> The firſt naturall, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Philoſophers in the Glaſſe of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures haue aſcended to the knowledge of one
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1641:19"/> Creator. The ſecond of grace, whereby the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the glaſſe of the Scriptures, know God as their Creator, and Redeemer. The third of glory, when the Saints ſhall ſee him face to face, as <hi>Paul</hi> that was caught into the third heauens, and there heard words not to be expreſſed. <hi>Prima viſio optat: Secunda odorat: Tertia guſtat.</hi> The viſion of nature wiſheth for that of grace: That of grace doth but ſalute that of glory: But in that of glory ſhall we ſee and taſte how gratious the Lord is.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The laſt reſemblance is in the ſecrecy of the way: One of thoſe things which the Wiſe-man admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, was<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 30.19.</note> 
                  <hi>the way of the Eagle in the ayre:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e occultatione.</note> See them flie we may; diſcerne their way we cannot. The Saints, their good workes are ſeene of men, but their intention, with what minde they doe them, is not diſcerned.<note n="k" place="margin">Greg moral. in Iob, lib. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>127.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Gregory</hi> notes, that our Sauiour ſaith; <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good workes, &amp;c.</hi> yet he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth againe, <hi>Take heed that you doe not righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to be ſeene of men;</hi> which he reconcileth, <hi>ſic opus fiat in publico, vt intentio maneat in ſecreto:</hi> Let your good workes ſhine, but not your inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Seeke not your owne glory; but that the ſpectators may glorifie your Father which is in heauen. Thus haue we viewed theſe fainted Ea-Nothing letteth but that now we may paſſe to the <hi>gathering together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In the vnfolded parable of the Sower, the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers are the Angels,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.</note> which ſhall <hi>gather the wheat into his garner,</hi> that is, the elect into his kingdome;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1641:20"/> and in another place, the<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.31.</note> 
                  <hi>Elect ſhall be gathered from the foure corners of the world:</hi> The world, the corners, the vtmoſt coaſts thereof ſhall be ſearched, that the Saints may be collected. The Eagle of a moſt ſwift ſlight, this gathering ſhall be ſpeedy; <hi>In a moment, in the tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nckling of an eye, at the last trumpe.</hi> And the Apoſtle,<note n="m" place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. <hi>vlt.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Rapte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur in nubibus,</hi> we ſhall be caught together in the clouds: as the lightning that cutteth the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſphaere</hi> from the Eaſt to the Weſt in a moment; ſo ſhall the comming of the Iudge be, ſuch ſhall the gathering together of the Eagles be.</p>
               <p>Here by the way, I may not ſcatter, what<note n="n" place="margin">Elector<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ast Math <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> hath gathered: How the godly are ſaid in holy Scripture to be gathered, and the wicked to be diſperſed. <hi>Gather thy Saints together,</hi> (ſaith the Prophet.)<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Let God ariſe, and his enemies ſhall be diſperſed,</hi> ſaith the ſame Prophet. The wicked are as chaffe which the winde ſhall ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.</note> The godly are as the Eagles which ſhall be gathered together: The memory of the wicked is likened vnto aſhes, becauſe of their diſperſion: but the iuſt ſhall be had in perpetuall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>place.</hi> The place is that the Diſciples moſt deſired to know, in which they are leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued; no ſet place ſet downe where theſe Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſhall be holden, but generally intimated, <hi>Vbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Hilar. in Mat. <hi>24.</hi> Canon. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>S. Hilaries</hi> opinion is; That he ſhall there iudge the world, where he ſuffered for the world. <hi>Illic claritatis adventus expectabitur &amp;c:</hi> Moſt fit
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1641:20"/> that his glory ſhould be there ſplendent; where it was moſt dazled with ignominie: where hee dyed as a malefactor, thereto iudge malefactors: where the Croſſe was, there the Tribunall to be. Therefore he ſaith, <hi>Where the dead body is,</hi> there ſhall be this gathering, this aſſembly.</p>
               <p>The Schoole-men generally affirme, That the place ſhall be the valley of <hi>Iehoſhaphat,</hi> grounding themſelues vpon that of <hi>Ioel;</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioel</hi> 3.2.</note> 
                  <hi>I will gather all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions together, and will bring them downe into the valley of Iehoſhaphat, will plead their cauſe &amp;c.</hi> And<note n="r" place="margin">Ribera comen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Ioel. cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ribera</hi> is ſo vehement for this opinion, that he demands, <hi>Qua fronte?</hi> With what a face any can reiect it? It being ſo ſutable to the letter, that<note n="*" place="margin">Nihil fere certum, aut ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploratum habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimus in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis.</note> we ſhall haue no certainty in the Scripture, if we forſake it.</p>
               <p>That there is ſuch a valley knowne by that name, on the Nor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h-ſide of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and at the foot of Mount Oliuet, Hiſtorians relate. But why it hath that denomination, ſeeing <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> was not there buried, but in the Citie of <hi>Dauid,</hi> none of them declar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">Supplem. <hi>4.</hi> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt q <hi>88</hi> art. <hi>4.</hi> Reſ ondeo, dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, non poteſt multum per cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinem ſciri, ſed probabiliter poteſt colligi ex Scripturis. Caluin. &amp; Gual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. in Ioel.</note>
                  <hi>Aquinas</hi> after he had ſaid what the Ieſuite out of him hath repeated, and ſomewhat more; yet doth not certainly determine, but probably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture that to be the place.</p>
               <p>And with <hi>Riberaes</hi> leaue, it is more conſonant to the literall ſenſe; That God will deliuer his people from the hands of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> to whom they were now captiuated: And that hee might comfort them the more, he doth allude to that miraculous victorie<note n="t" place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.</note> that God gaue to <hi>Iehoſaphat.</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:1641:21"/> For liſten <hi>Ribera,</hi> as the Lord did then cauſe a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill diſcord, and mutinie to ariſe in the Enemies campe, wherein the children of <hi>Ammon</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed thoſe of Mount <hi>Seir,</hi> therefore the place was called the valley of <hi>Beracah,</hi> or bleſſing: So is the Lord able to deliuer you out of the <hi>Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> yoke, and to gather you from among the Nations.</p>
               <p>Therefore whether Chriſt ſhall iudge in the ayre, or on the earth, in Mount <hi>Caluary,</hi> or in the Valley of <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hoſaphat,</hi> we place it <hi>inter ſcita Scholae,</hi> to be diſcuſſed in School<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, not <hi>inter articulos fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei,</hi> to be imbraced as an Article of our beleefe.</p>
               <p>The circumſtance of the place, <hi>where,</hi> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes me call to minde the time <hi>when</hi> the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall be, which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s much or more vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine then the former, ſo ſealed vp, that<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Math</hi> 24.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>of that day, and houre knoweth no man, no not the Ang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ls</hi> (ſaith our Lord) <hi>but my Father onely:</hi> It tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the knowl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dge of man: It tranſcendeth the knowledge of Angels; and (as it ſeemeth by Saint <hi>Mark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of the Sonne too; who addes,<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.32.</note> 
                  <hi>not the Sonne, but the Father.</hi> Of man there is no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, who is ignorant of many things he is bound to know: Neither is there any great ſcruple of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Angels; for though they ſee him that ſeeth all things, yet in him they doe not ſee all things, but thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obiects that concurre to their <hi>Beatitude;</hi> as the<note n="x" place="margin">Non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ad intel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> alia, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>14</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Schoole-men haue bounded that<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> too too large ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch of <hi>Gregory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doubt, all the ſcruple, and difficultie lyeth in Chriſt, how he ſhould be ſaid not to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1641:21"/> know the day of iudgement: Some haue thought this clauſe <hi>(neque filius)</hi> to haue beene crowded into the Text by the <hi>Arrians,</hi> and <hi>Agnoaetae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 42</note>
                  <hi>S. Gregory ad Eulogium</hi> layeth downe three expoſitions of the Fathers.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is, that it is not to be referred to Chriſt the head, but vnto vs the body; as in the Scripture by reaſon of the myſticall vnion things are; <hi>viz. Whatſoeuer you doe vnto theſe, you doe it vnto me.</hi> So it will be, Chriſt knew it not in his members, that is, the Church knew it not. But this is iuſtly diſcarded by<note n="z" place="margin">Bellar. lib. <hi>5.</hi> de anima Chriſti. cap. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine:</hi> for if Chriſt had not knowne it but in his members; why doth hee adde <hi>no man, no not the Angels;</hi> ſeeing men, and Angels are members of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall body.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, he knew it not, becauſe he hath not made vs to know it: As God ſaid to <hi>Abraham;</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Now I know thou fearest me;</hi> that is, I haue made thee, and all that know thee, for to know it: As we ſay, now the Sunne ſhineth clearely, now it is darkned: not that euer claritie is ſeparated from the body of the Sunne; but that ſometimes his light, and beames are withdrawne from vs. So we ſay, it is a ioyfull, or ſorrowfull day: not in it ſelfe, but becauſe it is to vs either ioyfull, or ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull. So our Sauiour knew not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath not made vs to know it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Chriſt knew this day <hi>in natura huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis,</hi> but not <hi>ex natura humanitatis:</hi> The man-Chriſt knew it; but not as man: <hi>in ipſa,</hi> but not <hi>ex ipſa;</hi> in the manhood, but not by the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1641:22"/> but ſpeciall priuiledge of reuelation.</p>
               <p>The<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>4.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>4.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Schoole-men tell vs of a twofold know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Chriſt; <hi>in verbo,</hi> and <hi>in genere proprio:</hi> The firſt, whereby he ſeeth all things in the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Word: The ſecond, whereby he ſeeth them in themſelues: And this againe is twofold; either <hi>infuſed,</hi> or <hi>acquiſite:</hi> His infuſed knowledge was powred into his manhood in the act of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, when all knowledge the finite creature could be capabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of, was granted vnto him, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reby he diſcerned all things. But beſides this, he had an acquiſite, and <hi>experimentall</hi> knowledge; whereby experience acquainted him with many things that practically he knew not before. And in this reſpect (if in any) may he be ſaid not to know the day of iudgement.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>nſt Vbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>q <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>One thing more occurres vnto mee: Chriſt ſaith not, <hi>Vbique corpus;</hi> but <hi>Vbicunque;</hi> not that his body is <hi>euery where,</hi> but <hi>whereſoeuer:</hi> As he tooke on him the nature of man, ſo that nature was finite, had all the properties of a created na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; therefore had an <hi>vbi,</hi> was contained within the limits, the <hi>ſuperficies,</hi> and bounds of place. Therefore <hi>locall motions</hi> are aſcribed vnto him in the Scripture; where he is ſaid to deſcend, and aſcend, and goe vnto the Father. And after his reſurrection; <hi>Surrexit, non est hic;</hi> He is riſen he is not here; therefore he is not <hi>euery where.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The monſtrous and new ſprung error of <hi>Vbi quitie</hi> (as<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> carnal cap. <hi>12</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> excellently obſerueth) euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all the Articles of our Creed, that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue touching the manhood of our Sauiour: of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1641:22"/> his conception, how could he be contained with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſtraites of bleſſed <hi>Maries</hi> wombe, if hee be in all places? how was he nayled to the Croſſe, if euery where? how wrapped in linnen cloathes? how intombed in a Sepulchre? if his body be ſo ſpacious that it knoweth no limits, how aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he into heauen? and<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 3.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> how doe the heauens containe him? if hee bee not contained in any compaſſe.</p>
               <p>It is true, we acknowledge a <hi>Communication of properties,</hi> and that not Rationall, but Reall; yet not of the natures, but perſonall vnion; not <hi>inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently</hi> in the natur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, but <hi>perſonally</hi> in the perſon of the Sonne of God: So wee ſay that Chriſt is euery where, and that the Virgins Sonne created the world, <hi>not by the propriety of natures, but by the communication of properties:</hi> as<note n="e" place="margin">Non per pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietatem natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum, ſed p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r communicatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem proprieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b. <hi>3.</hi> Sent. di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>22.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>2.</hi> Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d eſt diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> humanitati, aliud inhabitare. Bellar. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de Incar. Chriſti. cap. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bonauenture</hi> acutely. Neither are we ignorant of that of the Apoſtle, <hi>In him dwelleth the fulneſſe of the Godhead bodily:</hi> yet it is one thing to <hi>dwell,</hi> and another thing to bee <hi>communicated:</hi> becauſe of a mans dwelling in a houſe, the houſe cannot bee ſaid to goe, to ſpeake, &amp;c. but the man dwelling in the houſe: ſo not the body euery where, but the Godhead dwelling in the body.</p>
               <p>There is a being of Eſſence, and a being of Subſiſtence: the Eſſence of the Humanity is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, becauſe a creature. But the being of ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence hauing none of it owne, becauſe it ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in the perſon of the Sonne of God is infinit; ſo the finite humanity doth infinitely ſubſiſt in the Godhead; and in a ſenſe may be ſayd to bee
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1641:23"/> euery where: This with <hi>Zanchy</hi> doe I conceiue to be the mind of ſome of the Germane Diuines, and eſpecially that learned <hi>Chemnitius</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>Chriſts body then is locally in one place, but perſonally in al places, <hi>Salua vtriuſque naturae pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietate,</hi> ſaith the great Councell<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> it hath his <hi>vbi,</hi> not <hi>vbique,</hi> not euery where, but whereſoeuer: ſo ſaith my Text; <hi>Vbicunque fuerit corpus, &amp;c. Whereſoeuer the body is, thither will the Eagles be gathered together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus haue I now done with the abſolute, and Theoreticall <hi>explications</hi> of this Text: paſſe I now vnto thoſe more reſpectiue, and paſſionate <hi>applications,</hi> wherein I ſhall implore for Heauens aſſiſtance, and your patience for the continuance thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>1</label> The Eagles are gathered to the dead body, but for food: Chriſt, ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Comment. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Gorran,</hi> is the prey of Eagles: <hi>The Eagle</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iob</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>lib</hi> 6 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>) <hi>ſeeketh her prey, her eyes behold it afarre off, her young ones alſo ſucke the blood; and where the ſlaine is, there is he.</hi> The im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculate Body that was ſlaine, the precious blood that was ſpilt, the Eagles and the young ones, the fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thfull, and the faithfull branches, doe eate the one, ſucke the other, and are refreſhed.</p>
               <p>In the<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.35.</note> ſixt of <hi>Iohn, I am</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>the bread of life, he that commeth vnto me ſhall neuer hunger, and hee that beleeueth on mee ſhall neuer thirſt.</hi> The Iewes did eate of that food, the like to which no Nation did euer eate; yet they loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed this ſpirituall Manna, the like to which they
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1641:23"/> neuer taſted. This bread (ſaith<note n="k" place="margin">Aug. tract. <hi>26.</hi> in Ioan.</note> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) is the bread of righteouſneſſe: and accordingly doth our Sauiour ſpeak, <hi>Bleſſed are thoſe that hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſſe:</hi> and to come home to Chriſt, this righteouſneſſe is Chriſt,<note n="l" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.</note> 
                  <hi>who is made vnto vs righteouſneſſe,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle: And this righteouſneſſe is Manna from Heauen, <hi>Quam dat Deus, non quam ſibi facit homo;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug.</note> which God giueth, not which man doeth. This bread then is Righteouſneſſe; this Righteouſneſſe is Chriſt; this Chriſt is the Body; this Body is a dead Body; on which the holy Eagles feed, and are refreſhed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6 51.</note> 
                  <hi>any man ſhall eate of this bread, he ſhall liue for euer: the bread that I will giue is my fleſh, which I giue for the life of the world.</hi> If any man eate of it; not <hi>qui premit dente,</hi> but <hi>qui credit mente;</hi> not <hi>orally</hi> by the body, but <hi>mentally</hi> by faith; the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy of it, <hi>he ſhall liue for euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The woman<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.</note> of Samaria, when Chriſt told her of the water, that hee would giue, which ſhould ſo quench her thirſt, that ſhe ſhould neuer thirſt againe: <hi>Lord</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>giue me of this wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that I neuer thirſt:</hi> She had but a carnall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit. Let vs lift vp our ſoules, our hearts, our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, our all, to feed on this bread of life. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>non in ſolo pane, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Man liueth not by bread alone, but by euery word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God. Diues</hi> fared delicately, but his ſoule was ſtarued; one drop of the water of grace would haue yeelded more comfort to his tormented ſoule, then all the variety wherewith
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1641:24"/> here he was ſatiated. How many of vs glut the body with pompous fare, and in the interim ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the ſoule to periſh for want of ſpirituall food. Oh ſuffer not your ſoules, your ſelues to periſh: here is refreſhing,<note place="margin">Aug vt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Qui vult viuere, habet vbi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat, habet vnde viuat:</hi> Hee that would ſee, and liue many good dayes; he hath where he might liue, wherewith he might liue. <hi>Labour</hi> (ſaith our Lord) <hi>not for the meat which periſheth, but for the meat which periſheth not. Sic homo laboret in terra, vt poſtea regnet in Coelo:</hi> Oh man ſo labour in this world, that thou maiſt liue in the world to come: Behold a Creator become a Redeemer; a Redeemer tooke a body; that body made a dead body, for the Saints to feed on, and bee refreſhed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>2</label> This property of reſorting to the carkas, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s communicated to the Rauens, and others; yet none named but the Eagles: The Eagle<note n="o" place="margin">Amb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. expoſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lo.</note> 
                  <hi>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit, humilia de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>clinquit:</hi> A<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. cap <hi>123.</hi> pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>84.</hi>
                  </note> Princely bird, of a piercing ſight, a ſwift, and lofty flight: vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Saints; who are Kings ouer their affections; rule their paſſions; contemne the world; and mount aloft after heauenly things.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Learne of the Eagle two things: firſt, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the world,<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſhe is euer mounting vpwards, and ſets light by the things that are below: She neuer condeſcendeth to any of theſe inferiour things, but when neceſſity compels, not when ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity lures her: Iuſt ſo is it with the Saints of God, that vſe this world as if they vſed it not:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1641:24"/> wherewith to ſupply their neceſſary wants, and no farther.</p>
               <p>Such Eagles were, <hi>Zacheus,</hi> that left his extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Matthew</hi> his toll-gathering, <hi>Peter</hi> all: <hi>Nec invtilis commutatio omnia relinquere proco qui ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra omnia,</hi> ſaith bleſſed<note n="q" place="margin">Ber. de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am. ſuper E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mus &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Bernard.</hi> A happy change to leaue all, for him who is worth more then all: for what fruit, or profit is there in coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe things that will away. <hi>Quae etſi non deſerant, deſerenda ſunt;</hi> ſaith<note n="r" place="margin">Leo ſer. <hi>5.</hi> in Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Dom.</note> 
                  <hi>Leo.</hi> Say they leaue not vs, yet we muſt take our leaue of them.</p>
               <p>The Eagles catch not at flyes; the Saints catch not at the flies of this world, that flie away, and leaue nothing behinde them, but remorſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; <hi>Quod tangit,</hi> the thing that did touch them with pleaſure paſſeth: <hi>Quod angit,</hi> the ſting that pricks them ſtill remayneth. How much doe many, that would be accounted Eagles, degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from theſe celeſtiall Eagles, that are ſo graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſo linked to the world; ſo ſcrewed, ſo glewed to their riches: When they are awake, they ſigh how to come by riches; when they are a-ſleepe, they dreame how to preſerue them ſecurely: And ſo <hi>nec vigiliae laetae, nec ſomnus ſecurus,</hi> ſaith Saint<note n="ſ" place="margin">Hom. de miſ: &amp; duabus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duts.</note> 
                  <hi>Chryſostome;</hi> neither quiet when they are awake, nor well at eaſe when they are a ſleepe.</p>
               <p>Contemne, contemne this world: <hi>If riches in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, ſet not thy heart vpon them:</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Praefat. affix. lib. de Conſid. ad Eugen.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Bernard</hi> hoped of his ſcholler <hi>Eugenius,</hi> (though he were aduanced from a poore Monke to be Biſhop of <hi>Rome:</hi>) that <hi>In ſe facta eſt mutatio, non de ſe:</hi> In that change, he was not changed. The Saints
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1641:25"/> though their eſtates be changed, yet they are not changed: Their deſire is not to be <hi>rich vnto this world, but vnto God.</hi> He is truly rich that aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth more in mercy, then in ſubſtance: In giuing, then in taking: In commending his riches to heauen,<note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſoſt. vt ſupr.</note> rather then to this world. <hi>Qui ad hoc viuit vt operetur, ad hoc operatur, vt in aeteruum viuere mereatur:</hi> That liueth to worke, worketh to merit; merit, that he might liue for euer. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto <hi>Chryſostome.</hi> And hitherto of the firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie, wherein we are to imitate the Eagles.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rne ſecondly of them a <hi>Surſum corda,</hi> to mount with the Eagles. The ſpirituall man hath his eleuations, whereby he is eleuated aboue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: ſo <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 5.1. <hi>P a.</hi> 12 1.</note> 
                  <hi>I lift my heart vnto thee:</hi> and in another place, <hi>I haue lifted vp mine eyes vnto the mountaines:</hi> Some lift vp their eyes without their hearts, as the Phariſie, that <hi>drew neere with his lips, &amp;c.</hi> Others, their hearts without their eyes, as <hi>Annah,</hi> that prayed in her heart, without any vocall ſound: Some lift vp their hearts, hands, and eyes, inward integrity, and outward profeſſion; of whom the Apoſtle ſpeaketh,<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>our conuerſation is in heauen.</hi> And <hi>vere clati, quorum conuerſatio in coelis,</hi> ſaies <hi>Gregorie.</hi> Such a one was <hi>S. Paul; In terra poſitus, à terra extraneus:</hi> Liued here, yet a ſtranger while he liued here. The Saints liue here, but haue their conuerſation in heauen: <hi>Corpore ambulamus in terra, corde habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamus in coelo,</hi> ſaies<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Anſelme:</hi> Their bodies here, their hearts in heauen; ſuch is their eleuation.</p>
               <p>The Saints as they haue their <hi>elevation,</hi> ſo haue
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1641:25"/> they their aſcenſions. <hi>Eſay</hi> inuites vs to it:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Come let vs aſcend into the Mountaine of the Lord.</hi> And<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l.</hi> 15.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> demandeth, <hi>Lord who ſhall aſcend into thy holy Mountaine, or who ſhall dwell in thy holy hill?</hi> Heauen is a hill; therefore we muſt climbe: Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is a mountaine; therefore we muſt aſcend. Faith, and good workes, prayer, and giuing of almes aſcend; <hi>Let my prayer be directed into thy ſight as the Incenſe:</hi> And to <hi>Cornelius, Thy prayer, and thy almes-deeds haue aſcended,</hi> or <hi>come vp be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We are grafted</hi> (ſaith<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> the Apoſtle) <hi>into the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of his reſurrection:</hi> So by the ſame Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, are we inſerted into the likeneſſe of his Aſcenſion: (<note n="*" place="margin">Preached on Sunday next aft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion day.</note> The F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt of the Aſcenſion ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll bleeds in our mindes.) Let vs therefore erect the eyes of our hearts to that height, whither Chriſt is aſcended. It is the Apoſtles own Reaſon;<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſ.</hi> 3 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Seeke thoſe things that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e aboue, where Christ ſitteth at the right hand of God:</hi> Thither direct your thoughts, whither Chriſt is aſcended: <hi>Ad aeterna praedectos, peritura non occup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt:</hi> Let not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary affaires poſſeſſe your ſoules, that from <hi>eternitie</hi> are elected to <hi>eternitie:</hi> Let not deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſnares make vs ſlacke our pace: And thoſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and ſinnes, that may ſeeme faire and profitable to intice vs: <hi>Non amplect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nda nequiter, ſed tranſcunda ſunt fortiter,</hi> (ſaith<note n="b" place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>dent &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> fidel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s haec <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mp ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ur, vt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ri ſe in hac valle mundi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ant: in qua etiamſi quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam commoda blandi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntur, non ampl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilenda ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiter, ſed tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeunda ſunt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titer. Leo ſer. <hi>2.</hi> de aſcenſ. Dom.</note> 
                  <hi>Leo:</hi>) Let vs not wickedly embrace th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, but valiantly let them goe:<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1.</note> Let vs lay aſide <hi>euery weight, and ſin that doth ſo eaſily beſet vs, and runne with patience the race that is ſet before vs.</hi> Let vs ſhake off the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1641:26"/> fetters of ſinne from the feet of our affections; the duſt of vanity from our wings, and flie vnto the Lord like vnto the Eagles.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In the third place: Let vs gather all the powers of our ſoule together, to call to minde this <hi>gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring together.</hi> A generall aſſembly, the greateſt Aſſiſes that euer were holden, where and when all of vs muſt make our perſonall appearance: <hi>for we must all appeare before the tribunall throne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 5.10.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. When the Lord of heauen ſhall ſend forth his proceſſe, no <hi>Non est inuentus,</hi> ſhall be then returned; no appearing by Attour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; no pleading by an Aduocate; but <hi>corpus cum couſa</hi> ſhall be then produced.</p>
               <p>This myſterie was reuealed vnto <hi>S. Iohn:</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 20.12.</note> 
                  <hi>And I ſaw all both great, and ſmall, ſtand before the Throne, and the bookes were opened, &amp;c.</hi> Though neuer ſo great, yet they ſhall appeare before this great one; neither ſhall the ſmal ones be excluded: <hi>Great</hi> in grace, <hi>great</hi> in dignity, <hi>great</hi> in worldly preferment, <hi>great</hi> in ſinnes, howſoeuer <hi>great: Small</hi> in the worlds eye, <hi>ſmall</hi> in humble thoughts, how ſmall ſoeuer, they ſhall appeare. No exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, no exception, no priuiledge, all within the compaſſe of the Lords Iuriſdiction, all of vs owe ſuit and ſeruice to this Court: <hi>For we must all appeare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And there wee muſt be accountable for the things <hi>we doe here in the body.</hi> The workes that we now doe ſhall giue in euidence; if good, for vs; if bad, they ſpeake againſt vs. The tree ſhall be knowne, and iudged by his fruit; and as it
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1641:26"/> now falleth, ſo it lyeth. No adding to what we haue not done; no retracting that we haue done: Too late to goe buy oyle when the <hi>Bridegroome</hi> is come; or to get a <hi>wedding garment,</hi> when we haue ſet footing within the wedding houſe; no place for teares, no time for repentance: <hi>Poenite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, ſed fruſtra poenitebit;</hi> The wicked ſhall be penſiue, but their repentance comes too late.</p>
               <p>Call to minde our incorruptible Iudge, who will not be imbraced with gifts, allured by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, withdrawne by promiſes, deceiued by ignorance; to whom all things are naked. Say not (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) the walls are round about vs, we will ſinne: <hi>Eſto quod nemo te videat, non tamen nullus;</hi> Be it that no man ſee thee, yet he ſeeth thee, who is both <hi>teſtis,</hi> and <hi>Index:</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Chryſoſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de prouidentia Dei.</note> 
                  <hi>Neque enim tunc ouina pellis lupum;</hi> Our ſheep-skins ſhall not then couer our wooluiſh affections: <hi>Neque ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchri dealbatio internam coinquinationem;</hi> nor the outward painting, our inward rotteneſſe;<note n="f" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5.</note> 
                  <hi>for then the Lord will bring to light the hidden things of darkneſſe, and will make manifeſt the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of the heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider alſo, that our caſe is life, and death, and that not <hi>temporall,</hi> but <hi>eternall;</hi> all is at the ſtake: If the ſentence make for vs, then are we moſt happy; if againſt vs, moſt miſerable. In the ſentence of conſolation,<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 25.34.</note> euery word hath his efficacie of comfort: theres a louing call, <hi>Come ye;</hi> a diuine bleſſing, <hi>Come yee bleſſed;</hi> a fatherly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my Father;</hi> a retribution of reward, <hi>receiue yee;</hi> an aſſignment of a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1641:27"/> 
                  <hi>Receiue you the kingdome;</hi> a preparation of glory, <hi>prepared for you;</hi> eternall predeſtination, <hi>from the beginning of the world: I haue choſen you from the beginning of the world,</hi> therefore haue prepared you <hi>glory:</hi> haue prepared glory, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue aſſigned you a <hi>kingdome:</hi> haue aſſigned you a kingdome, for you are my ſonnes, and I am your <hi>Father:</hi> I am your Father, therefore you are <hi>bleſſed:</hi> you are bleſſed, therefore <hi>come yee:</hi> What a <hi>Iubilee</hi> of ioy will this cauſe in their bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hearts? They cannot but ſay within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, <hi>Thy word, O Lord, is ſweeter vnto vs, then the honie, or the honie combe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>And in the ſentence of condemnation, euery word ſtriketh dead vnto the heart: Firſt a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from God, <hi>Goe yee:</hi> a malediction, <hi>Goe yee curſed:</hi> a priſon, <hi>Goe yee curſed into:</hi> the ſharpnes of the paine, <hi>Goe yee curſed into fire:</hi> The durance of the ſame, <hi>into eternall fire:</hi> the grim ſocietie, <hi>with the deuill and his angels.</hi> This is <hi>durus ſermo,</hi> a hard ſpeech, who can endure it? No repealing of this ſentence, no appealing from this Iudge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Now the Lambe ſpeakes in mercy, who will not heare it? Then the Lyon ſhall roare in iuſtice, who will not feare it?</p>
               <p>Remember this, <hi>remember thine end, and thou wilt not ſinne. Dauid</hi> made Gods iudgements his obiect, his eyes were neuer off them;<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.22.</note> 
                  <hi>all his iudgements are in my ſight:</hi> And <hi>Solomon</hi> the ſonne trode his fathers footſteps;<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>ſ.</hi> 3.17.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſaid in my heart, God ſhall iudge the righteous, and the wicked:</hi> So all the Saints with <hi>S. Hierome,</hi> ſeeme to heare
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1641:27"/> alwayes the trump to ſound, with <hi>ariſe yee dead, and come to iudgement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is a <hi>memento</hi> for all; great, and ſmall ſhall ariſe; great, and ſmall are to remember it: to both of which I am a debtor, and now with Gods per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion my debt I will diſcharge.</p>
               <p>Firſt, you whom the Lord hath made great,<note place="margin">1. To great ones. An exhortation to the Iudges.</note> by communicating a parcell of his Regiment, looke vpon him who is vnto you, <hi>author, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplum:</hi> he that did erect you, is a patterne to direct you: your authority is great, your place eminent, your charge is great, and let me ſpeake it with your fauour, your account ſhall bee great.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cum creſcunt dona, creſcunt rationes donorum:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Greg.</note> when our talents are enlarged, our account is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed: the beaſts and ſuch vnreaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>non iudicantur, quia non iudicant:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ber.</note> They are not iudged, becauſe they cannot iudge: it is not ſo with man, whom he hath indowed with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to diſcerne, and ſo made euery priuate man a priuate Iudge: much leſſe with thoſe whom hee hath ſet apart to be Iudges. S. <hi>Bernard</hi> to<note n="k" place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid.</note> 
                  <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genius Papa, Blanditur cathedra? ſonat tibi offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, non otium:</hi> doth the chaire flatter thee? it cals to mind thy duty, not idlenes. What though thou art ſeated in an eminent place, where thou ouerlookeſt all? <hi>Enim vero proſpectus iſte procin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum parit, non ſomnium:</hi> it tels thee thou hadſt need to looke about thee; what place left for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired thoughts, where cauſes, and caſes; <hi>non leges, ſed lites;</hi> Solicitudes, and vexations of minds, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1641:28"/> ſpirits are ſtill before you: <hi>Et finis horum quid niſi aranearum telae?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vt ſupra.</note>The ſame Father demands of the ſame man, when art thou free? <hi>Vbi tutus? Vbi tuus?</hi> where art thou ſafe? where art thou thy ſelfe? Are not you alwaies poſſeſſed with cares, troubles, tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults: whither will you turne you from them;<note n="l" place="margin">Cicero pro Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia Poe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a.</note> 
                  <hi>pernoctant vobiſcum, peregrinantur, rusticantur:</hi> day, and night, at home and abroad, they euer at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend you: Certainly to a man that ſoberly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidereth theſe things, Your Honours are rather to be pittied, then enuied. And he rather com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſerateth your daily incumbrances; then repi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth at your ſplendent dignities.</p>
               <p>My Reuerend Lords, though theſe cares conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually beat at your doores, yet let contemplation of ſpirituall things modeſtly prompt you; That withdrawing your ſelues from the ſea of worldly affaires, you may with the <hi>Iſraelites</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtand ſtill vpon the ſhoare, and ſee the ſaluation of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Aguſtine</hi> ſpends a noble Chapter<note n="n" place="margin">lib. <hi>10</hi> de ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Dei, cap. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble worke wholly vpon this ſubiect: Though many are tyed ſo to attend worldly affaires, that in neglect thereof, they ſhould neglect their duty to Prince, and Countrey; yet none are ſo to bee oppreſſed with buſineſſe, as to forget their duty to God. He is not worthy to bee a Biſhop <hi>qui praeeſſe dilexerit, non prodeſſe:</hi> that loueth more to command, then to be commodious. He is not worthy to be a Iudge, that loueth more the prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence of his place, then to doe good in his place. Wherefore <hi>Ocium ſanctum quaerit charitas
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1641:28"/> veritatis:</hi> Loue of heauens truth deſires a holy leiſure: <hi>Negotium iuſtum ſuſcipit neceſsitas chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis:</hi> neceſſity of earths charity vndertakes iuſt affaires. So carry your ſelues betwixt contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and action, <hi>Vt nec ſubtrahatur iſta ſuauitas, nec opprimat illa neceſsitas:</hi> that the neceſſity of your actions doe not eclipſe the ſweetneſſe of your meditations; nor your meditations cauſe you to ſlacke your iuſt occaſions.</p>
               <p>Giue me leaue to commend vnto your thoughts two things: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt, the greatneſſe of your au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, as God hath lent you part of his power, ſo part of his title;<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.</note> 
                  <hi>I haue ſaid you are gods:</hi> and hee hath an eye after you, for it is in the ſame Pſalme, <hi>He iudgeth in the midſt of gods;</hi> or in the middle <hi>he iudgeth the gods,</hi> as<note n="*" place="margin">Hieron. expoſ. Pſal. <hi>81.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hierome</hi> reades it, and the Originall Hebrew will beare it: Awake then ye men of God, that are placed in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God: how dares corruption approach, bribery draw neere, peruerting of iuſtice enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the preſence of the all-ſeeing eye? thinke on this; The Lord doth behold your actions.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The 2. thing to be remembred is, that you haue this treaſure in earthen veſſels: A ſtrange, and true Epithite, you are <hi>mortall gods:</hi> Be not puffed vp with your high authority, and title: you <hi>ſhall dye like men,</hi> you ſhall riſe like men, you ſhall giue an account like men, you ſhall bee iudged like men; your now ouer-ſeer ſhall be then your Iudge; and who is preſent at your actions, ſhall ſentence you accordingly: Remember; you amongſt theſe Eagles ſhall be gathered together.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:1641:29"/>
               <p>Secondly to the ſmall, to all: remember that of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10.</note> 
                  <hi>When the heauens ſhall paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with a great noiſe, the elements ſhall melt with feruent heat, and the earth burne vp: what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men ought you to be in holy conuerſation and godlineſſe?</hi> Suppoſe now you ſhould ſee (as God knoweth how ſoone you ſhall ſee) the heauens to vaniſh with a great noiſe; The Elements with feruent heat to be diſſolued, and the earth in a fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie flame: Tell mee, what holy thoughts, and chaſt conuerſation would then poſſeſſe you. Saint<note n="q" place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>arrat. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pſal. <hi>49.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> expounding thoſe words of the Pſalme, <hi>Our God ſhall come, fire ſhall goe before him, and in his preſence a mighty tempeſt.</hi> Doth (ſaith he) the fire, and tempeſt fright vs? let vs be changed, and there is no cauſe of feare: <hi>ignem palea timet, auro quid facit?</hi> The Chaffe of ſinne ſhall be conſumed, the gold of piety ſhall be refined: <hi>ſtipulas ad te congeris? veniet ignis.</hi> Why heapeſt thou to thy ſelfe combuſtible mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Caſt away thy ſin, the fire hath not where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to burne, wherewith to worke.</p>
               <p>Tis very obſeruable Chriſt neuer treats of this ſubiect, but he addes a ſpeciall caueat; In Saint <hi>Mathew</hi> hee concludeth with the good,<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 24 45.</note> and bad ſeruant, the one expecteth his Maſters comming, and is bleſſed; Th'other, ſmites his fellows, eates, and drinkes with the drunken, and is accurſed. And in this Chapter, Remember<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.32.</note> 
                  <hi>Lots</hi> wife, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt not in doing good, leſt in looking backe to <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> Thou art intercepted; thy affections meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphoſed; and thou neuer turne from <hi>Sodom.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:1641:29"/>
               <p>Forget not the ſodainneſſe of his comming, as a thiefe in the night, nothing more vnexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; as the Lightning, nothing more ſwift; as the twinckling of an eye, nothing more ſpeedy.<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.26.</note> 
                  <hi>As it was in the daies of Noah, ſo ſhall it be in the daies of the ſonne of man. Noahs</hi> time, and ours alike in ſinne, alike in eating, drinking, alike in chambering, and wantonneſſe: The Preachers tongue would be defiled, Chriſtian eares would be offended, at the nomination of thoſe things that are done in ſecret. The face of the world in <hi>Noahs</hi> time was growne ſo filthy with ſin, that the Lord was conſtrained to waſh it with a flood: The droſſe of ſinne in our time doth ſo abound, that it muſt be purified with fire; And as then the vnexpected flood came and ſwept them all away, ſo the vnlooked for fire ſhall come when many leaſt dreame thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Noahs</hi> Fabricke was a reall Sermon, therefore Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſtiles him the Righteous Preacher: How many <hi>Noahs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 3.</note> and <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> cry vnto vs, <hi>Now is the axe laid &amp;c.</hi> Me thinkes I heare the ſons of <hi>Lamech</hi> ſcoffing at <hi>Noah,</hi> and his Arke, ſaying, what meaneth this fellow to ſaile on drie land: yet they could not laugh him out of his faith: we daily heare the ſcoffes of the inſenſible wicked at religious exerciſes; but <hi>Woe vnto you that laugh now, for you ſhall howle, and lament.</hi> Me thinkes I ſee the ſonnes of <hi>Lamech,</hi> how they came wading to the Arke middle-deepe, crauing admittance, but were denied; Methinkes I fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee the <hi>Hic-ſcorners</hi> of this age, knocking at Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1641:30"/> gate, crauing an entrance, but are repelled; with a <hi>Depart from me ye workers of iniquity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is then the houre ſo ſodaine? and nigh at hand? what meaneth ſinne thus to flouriſh? ſtill glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, ſtill carnality, ſenſuality ſtill, ſtill pride, ſtill vſury, oppreſſion, grinding of the poore; ſtill all, and more then all: I ſay no more, but with <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, <hi>Repent, and amend, for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God is at hand, When theſe Eagles ſhall be gathered together.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="exposition">
               <head>The fourth Expoſition.</head>
               <p>THere is yet the fourth ſenſe of theſe words, which I haue reſerued for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of all: and that is <hi>Gregories</hi> anago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall ſenſe; who interpreteth them of the life to come: Chriſt with his body is corporally aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into heauen; thither ſhall the Eagles bee gathered<note n="v" place="margin">Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſedi incarnatus ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er redemptor praeſideo: electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum animas cum ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne ſoluero: ad coeleſti: quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>: Greg. mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al. in Iob. lib. <hi>39.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note>: Hee is enthronized in the heauenly ſeat, thither will he lift vp his choſen alſo. This is that which hee ſpeaketh in<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12 26.</note> 
                  <hi>Iohn; Where I am, there ſhall my ſeruant be:</hi> and in the <hi>Apocalyps, To him that</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Reu. <hi>3.</hi> laſt.</note> 
                  <hi>ouercommeth, will I giue to ſit with mee in my throne:</hi> Our throne Chriſts, and Chriſts the Fathers throne; where we ſhall ſit; not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, but with him; <hi>with me in my throne:</hi> None ſhall bee with him, but his ſeruant; none ſhall ſit on his throne, but <hi>he that ouercommeth:</hi> none ſhall be gathered, but the Eagles.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:1641:30"/>
               <p>There ſhall our Eagles eyes behold him face to face, The Angels ſee him, and yet deſire to ſee him: <hi>Satiantes deſiderant, deſiderantes ſatiantur:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Greg.</note> they behold him their fill, yet ſtil deſire to behold him, and in his ſight there is fulneſſe of Ioy. This Pomgranate without dead ſeeds, this Roſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prickles, this wine not mingled with water: In Gods preſence the Seraphims burne with cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, the Cherubims are ſplendent with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. The Quire of Saints and Angels ſing Lauds, Hymnes, and ſpirituall ſongs. <hi>Peter</hi> at a glimpſe of this glory in the holy Mount cryeth out, <hi>Bonum eſt,</hi> it is good for vs to be here: then <hi>Ecce quam bonum,</hi> how good a thing it is to bee here for euermore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philip</hi> by a heauenly inſtinct, ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.8.</note> Lord ſhew vs the Father, and it ſufficeth; God is all-ſufficient to ſuffice. Honours, riches, &amp;c. are inſufficient. They that haue mounted to the top of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thinke ſtill <hi>vnum deeſt,</hi> one thing is wanting to perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Oh miſerable men how gape we after tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory and inſufficient glory, and neglect that onely which is immortall.</p>
               <p>You haue your fruit in holineſſe ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, but the end is eternall life:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Bonus finis vita aeterna, quae finem non habet;</hi> a good end indeed, of whoſe goodneſſe there is no end; there ioy without ſorrow, clarity without obſcurity, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie without wauering, plenty without ſurfet: Who will not mount with the Eagles to bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered to this glory? Infuſe, infuſe into our hearts thy grace (ô Lord) that with the wings
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1641:31"/> of Faith, Hope, and Charity, we may flie vnto thee, that we with all thy Eagles may be gathered to thy Kingdome, with thy Sonne; there to liue for euermore. To whom, and vnto thee, (ô Father) with thy bleſſed Spirit, three perſons, one inuiſible, and indiuiſible God be praiſe, and glory for euermore, AMEN.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laus Deo qui dedit velle, &amp; perficere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1641:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
